<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Online Home of Rajkumar</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/</link><description>Recent content on Online Home of Rajkumar</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 20:42:11 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rajkumaar.co.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Boredom, Books &amp; Bugs</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/boredom-books-bugs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 20:42:11 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/boredom-books-bugs/</guid><description>With millions of people stuck at home during the COVID-19 crisis, many explored various new hobbies to keep themselves occupied and ensure that they are not unduly stressed. According to a survey by The Healthy Work Company, a workplace mental health consultancy, 22% of respondents had taken up a new pastime in lockdown, while 35% had rediscovered an old one. In this article, I wanted to share my experiences on how I spent the past year locked inside four walls.</description></item><item><title>Building a J2EE app using IntelliJ Idea and deploying on Heroku</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/j2ee/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 12:23:35 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/j2ee/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s see how to build a basic Java Enterprise (fondly known as J2EE) application, made up of a Servlet and a JSP file, with the help of the popular IDE by Jetbrains, IntelliJ Idea. Finally, we will have a look at how to deploy the same on the Heroku cloud. 🌧
In the first place, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this blog because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a full-fledged write-up on how to do this myself initially and I had to try and err to find out the right way to do it.</description></item><item><title>Badgie - My first native GTK app</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/badgie/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 19:47:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/badgie/</guid><description>elementary OS has been my favourite Linux distro for quite a long time because of its beautiful UI, less bloatware which lets me focus on the work that needs to be done. After having used the OS, I wanted to contribute to it in some way or the other. And I started doing so by contributing to a currency converter app called Moneta which is available to download from elementary&amp;rsquo;s AppCenter.</description></item><item><title>Amrita Repository - Suite of Apps</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/amrita-repository/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 18:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/amrita-repository/</guid><description>In my first year of college, during the time of examinations more than 60% of my class used to pester those one or two guys who used to download the previous year question papers for reference from an intranet site (which still remains a mystery to most of the students). Being a hard-core techie, I wanted to bring an end to this and hence Amrita Repository was developed.
It started off as a Python CLI application providing access to only question papers which later extended itself to an android app and a telegram bot with much more helpful features.</description></item><item><title>Farewell at Internshala</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/internshala-farewell/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 19:35:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/internshala-farewell/</guid><description>Today was my last working day at Internshala and guess what! They sent me this picture as a farewell gesture! Looks amazing, isn&amp;rsquo;t it ? :D
Internshala is a technology company on a mission to equip students with relevant skills &amp;amp; practical exposure through internships and online trainings. Back in June 2018, when I was in my summer vacation after first year at college, all I knew was C and C++.</description></item><item><title>CodeChef Interview Experience</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/codechef-interview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 18:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/posts/codechef-interview/</guid><description>I’m a regular user at LinkedIn and I came across the Software Development Engineer Internship’s poster by CodeChef when I was browsing through the feed one day. CodeChef’s interview process is very different unlike most other companies including its parent Directi. Due to COVID-19, my whole interview process was virtual.
Online Coding Round at CodeChef – 3 hours 1st and 2nd question were of beginner level (Reference) 3rd question (Easy) – You are given an array A1,A2,.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/about/</guid><description>I am Rajkumar, an ambitious software engineer, ever in awe of the wonders that 0s &amp;amp; 1s could create. I started my development with mainly Android apps made out of Java, then got to explore web technologies such as Laravel, NodeJS, Angular etc.
The software I mostly use are :
Jetbrains suite of IDEs for development. Sublime Text for quick text editing. Sublime Merge for complex git stuff. Duckduckgo mostly, Startpage rarely.</description></item><item><title>Book Shelf</title><link>https://rajkumaar.co.in/books/shelf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rajkumaar.co.in/books/shelf/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>